A Finding Aid to the Paul Ryan papers, 1931-2009, in the Archives of American Art AAA.ryanpaul
Archives of American Art
Paul Ryan papers
1931-2009
AAA.ryanpaul
Archives of American Art
19.7 Linear feet
The Paul Ryan papers measure 19.7 linear feet and document Ryan's education and career as a pioneering video artist, theorist, writer, and educator. Records include school records, family papers, correspondence, writings, project files, video recordings, teaching files, printed materials, scattered photographs, and artwork by others. Organizational records are also found for the Earthscore Foundation, Earth Environmental Group, the Gaia Institute, and the Raindance Corporation, among others. The bulk of Ryan's professional work is documented in his writings and project files.
Ryan, Paul
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers and archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1931-2003 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 1, 20)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1965-2007 (2 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 3: Writings, 1955-2001 (6.8 linear feet; Boxes 3-10, 20)
Series 4: Organizational Records, 1968-1996 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 10-11, 20, OV 21)
Series 5: Project Files, 1968-2008 (6.5 linear feet; Boxes 11-17, 20, OV 21-22, 24, RD 26)
Series 6: Teaching Files, 1967-2008 (0.7 linear feet; Box 17)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1968-2009 (1.6 linear feet; Boxes 18-20, OV 23, 25)
Series 8: Artwork, 1965-2003 (0.1 linear feet; Boxes 19-20, OV 22)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Paul Ryan were donated to the Archives of American Art by Ryan in 2008.
Biographical/Historical note
Paul Ryan was a pioneering video artist, writer, teacher, and theoretician based in New York City and the Hudson Valley of New York State. Born in 1943, Ryan spent his early adulthood as a seminarian and later a member of the Roman Catholic order of Passionist monks, which he left in 1965. He eventually received a B.A. from New York University. During the Vietnam War, Ryan received conscientious objector status and studied with Marshall McLuhan at Fordham University as alternative service. It was McLuhan's influence that led Ryan to begin to explore the possibilities of the medium of video.
In 1969, Ryan participated in the landmark exhibition "TV as a Creative Medium" curated by Howard Wise, which served to link the kinetic art movement of the 1960s with the emergent medium of video art. The first exhibition in the United States devoted to video, "TV as a Creative Medium" signaled radical changes and defined an emerging artistic movement. In 1969 Ryan co-founded the Raindance Corporation along with Ira Schneider, Michael Shamberg, David Cort, Beryl Korot, Phyllis Gershuny, and others. Raindance was an influential media collective that proposed radical theories and philosophies of video as an alternative form of cultural communication. Influenced by the communications theories of Marshall McLuhan and Buckminster Fuller, the collective produced tapes and writings that explored the relation of cybernetics, media, and ecology. From 1970-1974, Raindance published the seminal video journal Radical Software, which provided a network of communications for the fledgling alternative video movement. In 1971, Shamberg published Guerrilla Television, a summary of the group's principles and a blueprint for a decentralization of television through access to public and cable programming. The original Raindance collective dispersed in the mid-1970s; the nonprofit Raindance Foundation continued into the 1990s. Ryan's core writings from the Raindance era were gathered into his 1973 publication Birth and Death and Cybernation, republished in 1974 as Cybernetics of the Sacred.
Ryan's work to develop alternative uses of video technology continued long after his involvement with Raindance. He began to implement his theories about the use of video monitoring and feedback within dynamic systems with the work that came to be known as the Earthscore Notational System. With Steve Kolpan and Bob Schuler, he founded the Earthscore Foundation, through which he raised money for the exploration and development of this applied practice. Earthscore, based largely on the writings of philosopher Charles Sanders Pierce and Gregory Bateson's work on cybernetics, provided the theoretical and logical underpinnings of both the ecosystem documentation and interpretation process, and the triadic rituals of interpersonal behavior, that became the core of Ryan's work for much of his life. These ideas were implemented in a wide variety of projects such as eco-channel design, video scores specific to certain locations, threeing projects exploring interpersonal behavior with video and computer technology, and a curriculum for combining media production training with environmental education.
Ryan later worked with organizations such as Talking Wood, The Earth Environmental Group, and Environment '89, (re-named in later years Environment '90, '91, and '92) to implement Earthscore systems and prototypes. He co-founded The Gaia Institute, hosted at Cathedral of St. John the Divine, and co-directed it from 1985-1991. The Institute fostered dialogs between science, religion, and art through workshops, lectures, exhibitions and events. He was an artist-in-residence for Earth Environmental Group in 1988 via a grant from the New York State Council on the Arts, and used the residency to carry out his video project "Nature in New York City," documenting city ecosystems and demonstrating how an eco-channel might work. Environment '89 organized a coordinated campaign for a cable channel devoted to the environment, the New York City Eco-channel for a Sustainable Tomorrow (NEST).
Ryan spent his later years as a professor of media production and theory at Savannah College of Art and Design, and then at the New School for Social Research. His work has been exhibited widely in the United States, including "The Primitivism Show" in The Museum of Modern Art (1984), "The American Century Show" at the Whitney Museum of American Art (1999-2000), and the Venice Biennale (2002). He died in 2013.
Scope and Contents note
The Paul Ryan papers measure 19.7 linear feet and document Ryan's education and career as a pioneering video artist, theorist, writer, and educator. Records include school records, family papers, correspondence, writings, project files, video recordings, teaching files, printed materials, scattered photographs, and artwork by others. Organizational records are also found for the Earthscore Foundation, Earth Environmental Group, the Gaia Institute, and the Raindance Corporation, among others. The bulk of Ryan's professional work is documented in his writings and project files.
Biographical materials include family papers, early correspondence among Ryan family members, school records, selective service records, photographs of Paul Ryan, and career documentation such as résumés, CVs, recommendation letters, and narratives written by Ryan describing his career. Records related to Ryan's time in the seminary and monastery include letters home during this period, and his letter of resignation from 1965.
Correspondence is mainly professional in nature, and spans Ryan's career. Correspondence between Ryan and family members is also found. Professional correspondence is found with Myrdene Anderson, Peter Berg of Planet Drum, Morris Berman, Avery Johnson, Marga Bijvoet, Thomas Berry, Lois Bianchi, David Dunn, Roberta Kevelson, Gerrit Lansing, Aldo Lira, Oliver Lowenstein, Chip Lord, Claude Ponsol, Jody Procter, Jodi Sibert, Phyllis Gershuny Segura, Michael Shamberg, and Marita Sturken. Corporate correspondence is found regarding job applications, manuscript submissions to publishers, and video submissions to museums and broadcasters.
Writings include mainly articles and notebooks by Ryan, but also drafts of books, lectures, poetry, short stories, a treatment for a television show, and writings by others in various genres. Most of Ryan's prose writing is theoretical in nature, although personal writings and notes from projects are also found. Articles include both published and unpublished writings, with some published multiple times under different titles. Over one hundred notebooks spanning forty years contain a variety of content including drafts of letters, articles, grant proposals, lectures, and other writings. Ryan's two major publications, Cybernetics of the Sacred and Video Mind, Earth Mind, are documented with drafts, contracts, correspondence with publishers, layout documents, and notes.
Organizational records include writings, correspondence, printed material, financial records, grant proposals, and other records concerning various organizations, collectives, and companies in which Ryan participated, mostly having to do with environmental advocacy, video production, or a combination of the two. Organizations with substantial records in this series include the Earth Environmental Group, the Earthscore Foundation, Environment '89 (and '90, '91, and '92), the Gaia Institute, and the Raindance Corporation, among others. Documentation is most comprehensive for The Earthscore Foundation, including by-laws, grant proposals, extensive writings, financial records, and printed materials.
Project files contain video recordings, production notes, photographs, proposals, correspondence, a computer program designed by Ryan, prints for exhibition, illustrations and designs, posters, circulars, contracts, and scripts. Many of the projects documented in this series relate to Ryan's many explorations of the use of video to monitor and interpret two seemingly different subjects, environmental change and human behavior in relationships, expressed through a ritual of interaction among three persons designed by Ryan and called "Threeing," or "Triadic Behavior." The most thoroughly documented projects in this series include "Nature in New York City," "New York City Eco-Channel for Sustainable Television (NEST)," Talking Wood (a publication that incorporated the project "Watershed Watch"), "Inventing Triadic Behavior" (also known as the "Triadic Tapes"), "Tethys"(with artist Bob Schuler), and "Video Wake for my Father," a performance for video that saw many iterations, including a private performance, a public performance, an edited video program, and a published script.
Video recordings are found for three projects, including "Nature in New York City," "Inventing Triadic Behavior," and a threeing workshop held at the Kitchen entitled "Video Variations on Holy Week." A printout of records in a videotape database kept by Ryan is found in this series, with a proposal for video preservation; the list of tapes includes those found in the collection as well as tapes not extant.
Teaching files include documentation of Ryan's work at Dalton School, Hudson School, the New School for Social Research, and Savannah College of Art and Design, and many other workshops and training programs Ryan taught. Included are grade books, correspondence, curricula, training materials, and reports. Two of his programs, the Black Rock Rangers at the Dalton School, and the Urban Conservation Corps Pilot Video Program involve the implementation of the Earthscore Notational System in school curricula.
Printed material includes books, newspaper clippings, conference programs and published proceedings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, film and video programs, flyers, periodicals, poetry publications, posters, and materials relating to the artist Al Robbins, which includes an obituary written by Ryan. Also found are publications of the Raindance Corporation, which include the book, Guerrilla Television (1971), and four issues of their magazine, Radical Software (1971-1972). Most of the printed material was either written by Paul Ryan, contains articles by Paul Ryan, or documents activities of Paul Ryan. Other materials found contain works by Ryan's associates and collaborators.
Artwork contains artists' books, doodles, illustrations, prints, and photographs by named and unnamed artists. None of the artwork in this series appears to be by Ryan. Notable is an artist's book entitled "Patterns" by Lida Zerella, which incorporates still images from Ryan's Triadic Tapes in a small album. Two illustrations are found by Claude Ponsot, who also illustrated many of Ryan's publications relating to Kleinform and threeing.
Anderson, Myrdene, 1934-; Berg, Peter, 1937-2011; Berman, Morris; Berry, Thomas, 1914-2009; Bianchi, Lois; Bijvoet, Marga, 1948-; Dalton School. (New York, N.Y.); Dunn, David; Earth Environmental Group.; Earthscore Foundation.; Gaia Institute.; Johnson, Avery; Kevelson, Roberta; Lansing, Gerrit; Lira, Aldo; Lord, Chip; Lowenstein, Oliver; New School for Social Research. (New York, N.Y.); Ponsol, Claude; Procter, Jody, 1943-1998; Raindance Corporation.; Robbins, Al; Savannah College of Art and Design.; Segura, Phyllis Gershuny; Shamberg, Michael; Sibert, Jodi; Sturken, Marita, 1957-; Zerella, Lida; Art--Study and teaching; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Illustrations; Monasticism and religious orders; Photographs; Prints; Video artists--New York (State)--New York; Video recordings; Writings
- Biographical Material, 1931-2003; Series 1; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1, 20
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes personal and family papers of Paul Ryan, school records, letters home written during his years as a Catholic monk, photographs, and documents summarizing Ryan's career, and other personal records.
  Family papers include certificates and early letters between family members other than Ryan, including a letter which appears to have been written on the occasion of his birth. Keepsakes include a vintage postcard of Niagara Falls and a "serenity prayer" card. Photographs are of Ryan, family, and friends and are mainly unlabeled snapshots, although a few photographs of Ryan himself are black and white prints which appear to have been made for publicity purposes.
  Also in this series are Ryan's bi-monthly letters home from the seminary and monastery where he lived in monastic communities between 1960 and 1965, as well as his resignation letter from the monastery and its response. A letter from the Selective Service documenting the completion of his obligation in 1969 is also filed in this series.
  School records include class notes from high school, seminary, and college; school papers; diplomas; transcripts; and school publications, some of which contain articles written by Ryan and articles about him as a student athlete.
  Arrangement note
  Additional family writings are found by Paul Ryan's brother Jim Ryan, a poet, in series 5, Project files and series 3, Writings. Additional letters between Ryan and family are found in series 2, Correspondence. A long essay written by Ryan about leaving the Passionist monastery is found in series 3, Writings. Additional writings by Ryan during his school years are also found in writings under the headings "poetry" and "short stories." Additional photographs are found in series 5, Projects.
  - Birth Certificate, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business Cards, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Calendars, 1985; 1987; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Career Narratives and Notes, circa 1974-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family Papers (Box 1)
    - Certificates, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence Among Family Members, 1931; 1961; 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Genealogy and Writings, circa 1940; 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pi Alpha Kappa News, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Identification Cards, 1986; 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Keepsakes, 1933; circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Family while at Seminary, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Family while at Monastery, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter of Resignation from Monastery, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Ryan, circa 1981-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, Personal, circa 1975-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Résumés, CVs, and Recommendations, circa 1973-2002 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Ryan's 50th Birthday Guest Book and Photo Album, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - School Records (Box 1)
    - Class Notes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Class Notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Class Notes, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Class Notes, circa 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25-28)
    - Diplomas, 1960; 1953 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Diplomas, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - High School Football Team Photograph, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - School Papers, circa 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Scrapbook of Student Sports Activities, 1957; Scrapbook disassembled. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Oversized material housed in Box 20.
    - Seminary Newsletter, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Transcripts, 1958-1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Selective Service Record, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Service Award, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Oversized Scrapbook from Box 1, folder 33 (Box 20)
- Correspondence, 1965-2007; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Letters regarding institutional relationship with Ryan filed by corporate name; otherwise letters are filed by personal name. Correspondents with 3 or more letters have their own folders. Otherwise letters are filed in a general alphabetical file. Significant correspondents in general files are noted in the folder listing. Where outgoing letters written by Ran were found alongside incoming letters, the outgoing and incoming letters are kept together under correspondent's name. Otherwise, Ryan's outgoing letters and drafts of letters are filed chronologically under Ryan's name. Letters signed only with first names, unsigned, and illegibly signed letters are filed at the end of the series.
  Letters from Ryan to his family during his years in the monastery (1960-1964) are found in series 1, Biographical materials, as are letters among Ryan's family members written before he was born. Additional correspondence concerning Ryan's professional life is found in Series 4, Organizational Records, Series 5, Projects, and Series 6, Teaching Files.
  Series contains both personal and professional correspondence between Ryan and family members, friends, collaborators, and other colleagues. Professional correspondence is found with Myrdene Anderson, Peter Berg of Planet Drum, Morris Berman, Avery Johnson, Jack Burnham, Red Burns, Bob Harris, Marga Bijvoet, Thomas Berry, Lois Biachi, David Dunn, Roberta Kevelson, Gerrit Lansing, Oliver Lowenstein, Aldo Lira, Chip Lord, Claude Ponsol, Jody Procter, Jodi Sibert, Phyllis Gershuny Segura, Michael Shamberg, Marita Sturken, and Howard Wise. Corporate correspondence is found regarding job applications, manuscript submissions to publishers, and video submissions to museums and broadcasters.
  - A, 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Alternative Media Center, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Anchor Press (Doubleday), 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Myrdene Anderson, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - B, 1969-2005 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Gregory Bateson, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Peter Berg (Planet Drum), 1969-1997 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Thomas Berry, 1973-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Maury Berman, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lois Bianchi (WNET/Thirteen), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Marga Bijvoet, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - John Brockman, 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jack Burnham, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Red Burns, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - C, 1968-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Craig Cassarino, 1975-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Linda Crane (Parker), 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - D, 1969-2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Anne Marie Dinesen, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Anne Donnellan, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Joseph Drexel, 1970-2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - David Dunn, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - E, 1969-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - East West Journal, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tom Erlich, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - F, 1973-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fordham University, 1969-2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - H. Allan Friederiksen, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - G, 1973-2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes letter from Al Gore.
  - Jean Gardner, 1987-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Frank Gillette, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Vic Gioscia, 1971; 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Eric Gustafson, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - H, 1969-2004 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bob Harris, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Harry Frank Guggenheim Foundation, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Mike Helm, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mikhail Horowitz, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Hudson School, 1983-1998 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - I, 1968-1999 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - J, 1978-2000 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Includes letter from Steve Jobs.
  - Jerome Foundation, 1983-1997 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Foundation, 1975-1991 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Avery Johnson, 1970-1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - K, 1969-2001 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Includes correspondence with The Kitchen.
  - Roberta Kevelson, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Professor Dr. Rolf Kloepfer, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Richard Kostelanetz, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Betty Kronsky, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Lawrence Kugelman, 1990-2006 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - L, 1969-2000 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Oversized broadside filed in box 20.
  - Gerrit Lansing, 1983-2000 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - LACE (Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Leonardo: Journal of the International Society for the Arts, Sciences, and Technology, 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Aldo Lira, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Chip Lord, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Oliver Lowenstein, 1991-2000 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - M, 1965-2000 (Box 2, Folder 53-54)
  - Martin Marty, 1988-1996 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Dominique Mazeaud, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Museum of Modern Art (Barbara London), 1984-2002 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Museum of Modern Art Oxford, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - N, 1969-2005 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1970-1994 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - The New School, 1985-2000 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - North American Conference on Christianity and Ecology, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - O, 1968-2000 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Gerald O'Grady, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Oxford University Press, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - P, 1974-2006 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Contains correspondence with Nam June Paik and Walker Percy.
  - Pennsylvania State university, 1992-1999 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Peter Lang Publishing Incorporated, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Perice Edition Project, Indiana University, 1987-2006 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Planet Drum, 1983-2004 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    See also Peter Berg correspondence in Box 1, folder 44.
  - Claude Ponsot, 1965-2006 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Jody Procter, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Q, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - R, 1968-2004 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Restoring the Earth, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Peter Reynolds, circa 1988-1997 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation, 1974-1990 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Beth Ryan, 1978-1993 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Jim Ryan, circa 1974-2003 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Margaret Ryan, 1977-1991 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Paul Ryan, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Paul Ryan, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Paul Ryan, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Paul Ryan, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Paul Ryan, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Paul Ryan, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)